Miłosz mss., 1952-1994 LMC 2640
Lilly Library
Miłosz mss.
1952-1994
Lilly Library
Miłosz, Czesław
Zweig, Paul
LMC 2640
1 Box
The Miłosz mss., 1952-1994, consist of the writings, publicity, and correspondence of poet, translator, and diplomat Czesław Miłosz.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchase: 2006
Biographical Note
Czesław Miłosz, 1911-2004, was a Polish-American poet, translator, professor, and diplomat. Born into a prominent Polish family in modern-day Lithuania, Miłosz and his family were forced to move a number of times throughout his adolescence due to his father's involvement in the Polish-Soviet War. During his time as a law student at Stefan Batory University, Miłosz took an interest in poetry and socialism; throughout World War II, he published several clandestine volumes of poetry and aided Jewish citizens through an underground socialist organization via transportation and financial support. After the war, he served as a cultural attaché for the People's Republic of Poland, promoting and organizing Polish cultural events internationally. Miłosz was granted political asylum in France after defecting from Poland under Stalin's rule, and he moved to California to accept a visiting lecturer position at UC-Berkeley in 1960. During this time, Miłosz strove to bring Polish poetry into the English canon, publishing and translating a number of volumes. In 1980, Miłosz was awarded the Nobel Prize in Literature.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes materials regarding Miłosz's defection from Poland, including an offprint of his autobiographical essay "A Poet Who Fled Communist Poland," distributed by the American Committee for Cultural Freedom. Also included are broadsides of Miłosz's poetry as well as typescripts and proofs of his works, along with related publicity and reviews. A small number of signed letters to Paul Zweig, Stephen Berg, and James Goldwasser complete the collection.
The collection was acquired with books written and/or translated by Miłosz, as well as journals and magazines featuring his work, which are catalogued separately.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following series: I. Correspondence and II. Publications.
Related Materials
See Miłosz mss. II, also located at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
Polish poetry; Polish literature; Autobiography; Slavs
- Correspondence
  - Milosz to Rolando Pieraccini, 1984-1994 (Box 1)
  - Milosz to Mr. Ritner, 1965-1968 (Box 1)
  - Milosz to Roy Roberts, 1968-1973 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1974-1984 (Box 1)
- Publications
  - Czeslaw Milosz, "A Poet Between East and West," Michigan Quarterly Review, vol. XVI (1977), pp. 263-271 (Box 1)
  - Louis Iribarne (translator), The Issa Valley: A Novel by Czeslaw Milosz (Chapters I-XIX) (Box 1)
  - Charles Simic, "On Milosz" (Box 1)
- American Committee for Cultural Freedom Newsletters, 1952 (Box 1)